Jonathan Webster Papers Finding Aid
Oskar Diethelm Library
Jonathan Webster Papers
1824 - 1849
This collection contains the papers of Jonathan Webster, a mesmerism practitioner. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
.84 linear feet (2 boxes)
Webster, Jonathan Palmer
Oskar Diethelm Library DeWitt Wallace Institute of Psychiatry: History, Policy and the Arts Weill Cornell Medical College 525 East 68th Street, Box 140 New York, NY 10065
1968.0001
A cigar case with a portrait, possibly of a figure in the history of mesmerism, has been removed to the objects collection.
The Jonathan Webster Papers were purchased in June 1968 from Howard S. Mott Rare Books in Sheffield, Massachusetts with funds provided by Mr. and Mrs. Charles H. Blatt.
There are no access restrictions on this material.
Jonathan Palmer Webster (sometimes called “Dr.") was a mesmerism practitioner and hypnotist. Webster gave many public lectures, demonstrated experiments, and taught courses on these subjects, phrenology, and penmanship.
Webster, Jonathan Palmer; Spiritualism; Phrenology; Mesmerism; Hypnotism; Animal magnetism; Magnetic healing; Magnetism; Calligraphy; Penmanship
Most of the Webster collection dates from the 1840’s when he was actively engaged in presenting lectures and demonstrations on mesmerism. Manuscript materials include his writings on mesmerism and phrenology, prospectuses with names of subscribers to the courses and record of payment, testimonials signed by participants in his courses, and a record book indicating places Webster practiced phrenology, amount of money received, and names of some individuals examined. There is also material relating to his career as an instructor of calligraphy, such as examples of his penmanship style.
The printed and published documents include broadsides and posters announcing lectures on mesmerism and phrenology, including demonstrations of painless dentistry. Some of the broadsides announce other practitioners, including Dr. Boynton and Louis De Bonneville. There is a scrapbook of news clippings about his courses on mesmerism, in addition to publications about various aspects of mesmerism, magnetism, and phrenology, including one he authored entitled, “A Treatise on Phrenology.” These publications date from 1824 to 1849, with the majority from the 1840’s. The collection has no series and needs to be reprocessed.
- No series
  - Admission tickets to Webster's lectures on mesmerism, Undated (Box 1)
  - “A Treatise on Phrenology embracing a Chart, By P. Webster, Professor of Phrenology”, 1843 (Box 1)
  - Webster's writings on phrenology, Undated (Box 1)
  - Prospectus for Webster’s course on mesmerism with names of subscribers and record of payment, c. 1843 (Box 1)
  - Testimonials for Webster’s course on mesmerism signed by subscribers to the lectures, 1843 - 1847 (Box 1)
  - Record book indicating places Webster practiced phrenology, amount of money received, and names of some individuals examined, c. 1841 (Box 1)
  - List of debtors at Webster's writing schools, 1837 - 1842 (Box 1)
  - Essay on colic written by Mr. Dow, Undated (Box 1)
  - Notes about nitric muriatic acid, not written by Webster, Undated (Box 1)
  - Webster's drawing of a phrenological chart, Undated (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing Webster's writing and drawing academy, 1842 (Box 1)
  - Three examples of Webster's penmanship, Undated (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing lectures and exhibitions on phrenology given by Webster, Undated (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing lectures and experiments on mesmerism given by Webster, 1843 (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing lectures and experiments on mesmerism given by Webster, 1844 (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing lectures and experiments on mesmerism given by Webster, 1845 - 1847 (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing lectures and experiments on mesmerism given by Webster, Undated (Box 1)
  - Posters announcing lectures and experiments on mesmerism given by Webster, Undated (Box 1)
  - Broadsides announcing lectures and experiments on mesmerism and phrenology given by Dr. Boynton and Louis De Bonneville, 1844 - 1847 (Box 1)
  - Publication on phrenology including etchings by D. C. Johnston, 1837 (Box 1)
  - Scrapbook of news clippings of Webster’s course on mesmerism, 1843 - 1847 (Box 2)
  - Publication, "A Treatise on Phrenology" by J. Palmer, 1843 (Box 2)
  - Publications on magnetism and mesmerism C – D, 1843 - 1847 (Box 2)
  - Publications on magnetism and mesmerism E – H, 1843 - 1846 (Box 2)
  - Publications on magnetism and mesmerism M, 1824 - 1849 (Box 2)
  - Publications on magnetism and mesmerism N – W, 1843 - 1846 (Box 2)
  - Publications on phrenology, 1837 - 1843 (Box 2)
  - New York Magnetic Journal, 1845 (Box 2)
  - Catalogs of medical instruments and books, 1846 (Box 2)
  - Publication re: phonetic stenography, 1847 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, c. 1843 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, c. 1843 (Box 2)